A Guide to the Ford Foundation records, Office of the President, Assistant to the President, Office Files of Waldemar Nielsen FA620
Rockefeller Archive Center
Ford Foundation records, Office of the President, Assistant to the President, Office Files of Waldemar Nielsen
1952-1955
1953-1954
Rockefeller Archive Center
Ford Foundation
Nielsen, Waldemar A.
FA620
2.64 Cubic Feet
Arrangement
The files are arranged by topic. Items within each folder are arranged in chronological order.
Scope and Contents
The Assistant to the President Office Files of Waldemar A. Nielsen document the Ford Foundation's preparations for and responses to the Reece Committee. These files, dated 1952-55 (bulk: 1953-54), show the Committee's charges against the Foundation and individual staff members; material on its grantees and Funds gathered by the Foundation; the responses to the Committee; summaries of media reporting of the investigation; and other Foundation correspondence, memoranda, prepared statements, and press releases.
While these files do not represent all of the documents that the Foundation staff members prepared, they seem to be a complete record of those compiled by the President's Office. The documents were created by H. Rowan Gaither, Jr., Bernard Gladieux, Jane Hinchcliffe, Porter McKeever, William McPeak, Waldemar Nielsen, and other staff members. Additional records were produced by individuals at Cravath, Swaine & Moore, Arthur Newmyer and Associates, and Earl Newsom & Co.
It is apparent that these documents are not in the order which they were used as active files. These records were selected, arranged, and numbered, presumably by Mr. Nielsen. Since the material is accessible in this order, no attempt was made to re-establish the original, working order of the files.
Photocopies of documents from the early Foundation years (c. 1936-50) were not retained with these records (this information duplicates records already in the Archives). Government documents and other available printed material was discarded. Foundation Staff and Consultant Reports were pulled and transferred to that record group. These reports are listed in Appendix A; cross-reference sheets mark the original location of the reports. In many cases, drafts of letters and reports have been retained since they reflect the meticulous care that was used in preparing the responses to Representative Reece's queries.
These files do not document Mr. Nielsen's other responsibilities as Assistant to the President or activities in any of his other positions at the Ford Foundation.
"The [Reece Committee] investigation continued for over a year and was conducted in a manner openly hostile to foundations. The research methods employed by the staff were crude, consisting largely of culling secondary source material to find evidence to support the prejudices of the Chairman. Sixteen days of public hearings were held -- largely confined to the foundation activities in the social sciences. With one exception, the witnesses invited to testify were known to be hostile to foundations and the studies supported by foundation. Foundation officials were given no opportunity to appear before the Committee.
"The Final Report, signed by only three of the five members, was devoted largely to a summary of the hearings, witness by witness. No effort was made to evaluate the evidence presented or to take cognizance of the written statements submitted by foundations....
"The minority report attacked the aims, methods, and actions of the Committee and its staff, and charged that the majority report contained false statements, half-truths and misleading information.
Joseph M. McDaniel, Jr. memo to McGeorge Bundy March 1, 1966
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Ford Foundation archive was deposited at RAC in 2011. Ford Foundation records, correspondence, reports, program files and officers papers were transferred to, and accessioned by, RAC beginning in 2011. Accessions continue as necessary.
Biographical / Historical
Waldemar A. Nielsen worked as a staff member of the Ford Foundation from 1952 through 1961. During the course of his tenure with the Foundation he held the following positions:
• October 1957, Associate Director, International Affairs
• May 1956, Executive Associate, Program Area I
• June 1953, Assistant to the President, Office of the President
• December 1952, West Coast Representative, Pasadena, CA
• October 1952, Staff Associate, Program Area V
Mr. Nielsen left the Foundation in 1961 to become President of the African-American Institute. He worked as a consultant to the Foundation on various occasions between 1961 and 1970.
Mr. Nielsen was born March 27, 1917 in Greensberg, Pennsylvania. He graduated from the University of Missouri in economics and received a bachelor of science degree in business administration from the same university that year. He received a master's degree in political science at the University of Wisconsin in 1940. Prior to his career at the Ford Foundation, Mr. Nielsen held the following positions:
• 1951-52, Director of the European Information Division, Office of the U.S. Special Representatives in Europe
• 1948-51, Deputy Director of the Information Division, Office of the U.S. Special Representative in Europe
• 1947-48, Special Assistant, Secretary of Commerce
• 1946-47, [public opinion pollster], Department of State
• 1940-43, Field Director, Division of Program Surveys - Department of Agriculture
Mr. Nielsen published two books about foundations: The Big Foundations (1972) and The Golden Donors (1985). He also published various articles in Public Opinion Quarterly, Harper's Magazine, the New Yorker, and the Journal of Social Issues.
Conditions Governing Access
Records more than 10 years old are open for research with select materials restricted as noted. Brittle or damaged items are available at the discretion of RAC.
United States. Congress. House. Select Committee to Investigate Tax-Exempt Foundations and Comparable Organizations
- Reece Committee Investigation (United States House Select Committee to Investigate Tax-Exempt Foundations and Comparable Organizations), 1952-1955; 1953-1954; I
  - Administrative Files, 1953 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Policies and Programs, 1953 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Fund for the Advancement of Education, 1953-1954 (Box 1, Folder 3-4)
  - Fund for Adult Education, 1953-1954 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Resources for the Future, 1953-1954 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Eastern European Fund, 1953-1954 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Intercultural Publications, 1954 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Behavioral Sciences, 1953-1954 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Michigan Fund, 1953 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - TV-Radio Workshop, 1953 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - MIT Center for International Studies, 1953-1954 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Grants-in-Aid and Fellowships, 1953 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Pre-investigation Literature, 1954 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Report on Foundations, 1953 (Box 1, Folder 15-16)
  - A Bibliography of the Foundation in the Modern World. Feder, Robert (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Cox Resolution (H.R. 561), 1952 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Answers to Cox Questionnaire (1 of 2), 1952 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Answers to Cox Questionnaire (2 of 2), 1952 (Box 2, Folder 19A)
  - Updating of Cox Questionnaire, 1953-1954 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Reece Resolution Speech and Debate, 1953 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Reece Committee - Rules of Procedure [1st hearing], 1954 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Reece Committee - Operations Plan, 1954 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Reece Committee - Members and Staff, 1953-1954 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Reece Committee - Staff Correspondence and Foundation's Replies, 1953-1954 (Box 2, Folder 25-26)
  - Inter-Office Memoranda, 1953-1954 (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Personnel - Biographical Data - 1 (Box 3, Folder 28-29)
  - Personnel - Biographical Data - 2 (Box 3, Folder 30-31)
  - Gladieux's Statement, 1952-1954 (Box 3, Folder 32)
  - Goodwin Statement, 1954 (Box 3, Folder 33)
  - Reece Committee - Staff Reports 1, 1953-1954 (Box 3, Folder 34-35)
  - Reece Committee - Staff Reports 2, 1953-1954 (Box 3, Folder 36)
  - List of Charges and Related Material, 1953-1954 (Box 4, Folder 37)
  - Advertising Council, 1953 (Box 4, Folder 38)
  - India, 1953-1954 (Box 4, Folder 39)
  - Ford Motor Company, 1954 (Box 4, Folder 40)
  - Summary of Testimony and Press Coverage, 1954 (Box 4, Folder 41)
  - Newmyer Reports, 1953-1954 (Box 4, Folder 42)
  - Press Coverage Summaries, 1953-1954 (Box 4, Folder 43)
  - Press and Radio Comment, 1953-1954 (Box 4, Folder 44)
  - American Legion Magazine Articles, 1952-1955 (Box 4, Folder 45)
  - American Mercury Articles, 1953-1954 (Box 4, Folder 46)
  - H.R. Gaither, Statement to Committee with Related Documents, 1954 (Box 5, Folder 47-48)
  - H.R. Gaither Reply to Reece Report, 1954 (Box 5, Folder 50)
  - Distribution Lists, 1954 (Box 5, Folder 51)
  - H.R. Gaither Thank You Notes, 1954 (Box 5, Folder 52)
  - Statements by Other Foundations, 1952-1954 (Box 5, Folder 53-54)
  - Additional Statements (outside Committee), 1953-1954 (Box 5, Folder 55)
  - Congressional Resolutions (other than Reece), 1953-1954 (Box 5, Folder 56)
  - Ford Foundation Expenditure on Reece Episode, 1954 (Box 5, Folder 57)
  - Summary and Evaluation of Reece Episode, 1954 (Box 5, Folder 58)
  - M.T. Moore Evaluation Study, 1955 (Box 5, Folder 59)
  - Proposed White Paper, 1954 (Box 5, Folder 60)
  - Facts Forum & Heritage Foundation, 1953-1954 (Box 5, Folder 61)
  - Senator McCarthy and other material, 1953 (Box 5, Folder 62)
  - Board of Trustees, 1952-1953 (Box 5, Folder 63)
  - Tax-Exemption Privilege, 1952-1954 (Box 6, Folder 64-65)
  - Grant-Making Policies and Procedures, 1951-1952 (Box 6, Folder 66)
  - Safeguards Against Subversion, 1953-1954 (Box 6, Folder 67)
  - Relations of the Foundation with Comparable Agencies, 1952-1953 (Box 6, Folder 68)
  - Tradition and Progress in a Changing Scene, 1953 (Box 6, Folder 69)
  - Fund for the Republic, 1953-1956 (Box 6, Folder 70-72)
  - Grantee Organizations and Individuals that have Caused Public Controversy (other than FR), 1952-1955 (Box 6, Folder 73)
  - Statutory and Non-Statutory Limitation and Control (other than the Internal Revenue Code), 1953-1954 (Box 6, Folder 74)
  - Graphic Data, 1953-1954 (Box 6, Folder 75)
  - Press Comment, 1953-1954 (Box 6, Folder 76-77)